原视频名：50 Year Old Rocket Flies, Russia & China Announce Cooperation on Moon Base
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/Grkhla6CoHw
原视频发布日期：20210616
字幕翻译：旋火
Hello, it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
It's still in Hawaii at a place called the End of the World,
现在还在夏威夷一个叫世界末日的地方
which well, I'm sure it's pretty apocalyptic when there's some serious waves
我敢肯定 如果海况恶劣的时候 这里会是相当地世界末日
but it's pretty chill right now.
但现在还很平静
So a few things have been going on in space that I probably should talk about
因此 在太空中发生了一些事情 我也许应该谈一谈
just because they're interesting.
只是因为它们很有趣
First of all we had a launch, that was actually quite a surprise.
首先 进行了一次发射 这实际上是一个很大的惊喜
It came on to our calendars only a couple of months ago.
仅仅几个月前才出现在我们的日历上
The US Department of Defense launched a satellite on a Pegasus XL rocket.
美国国防部用飞马座XL火箭发射了一颗卫星
And I have previously declared the Pegasus XL dead.
而我之前已经宣布飞马座XL已经死亡
So you might think, wait a second, I thought you said it was dead.
所以你可能会想 等一下 我以为你说它已经死了
There is some question asked to the future of Pegasus XL
对飞马XL的未来有一些疑问
because it is still very overpriced,
因为它的价格仍然很高
2810万美元，差不多是之前发射的一半价格
spaceflightnow.com/2021/03/17/northrop-grummans-pegasus-rocket-selected-for-responsive-launch-demo/
as it happens, the Department of Defense got this at a bargain, basement price.
碰巧的是 国防部以低廉的价格得到了这个东西
I would, some would say, a going out of business price,
我想 有人会说 这是一个即将倒闭的价格
because these were Pegasus that had been built for the Stratolaunch project
因为这些飞马座是为平流层发射系统项目建造的
and of course had never flown.
当然那也没有飞过
But what's interesting was that this launch of a payload was put together in a very short time.
但有趣的是 这次有效载荷的发射是在很短的时间内完成的
The payload was built inside of a year.
这个有效载荷是在一年内制造完成的
And to demonstrate rapid re-launch capabilities,
而且为了验证快速再发射的能力
they didn't tell the launch provider when it was going to be launched
他们没有告诉发射商它将在何时发射
until like a month or so before the actual launch.
直到实际发射前一个月左右
But apparently Northrop Grumman, who now owns Pegasus,
但显然诺斯罗普·格鲁曼是目前飞马座火箭的拥有者
it was originally built by Orbital, which merged with ATK to be Orbital ATK.
它最初是由轨道公司建造的 该公司与ATK合并成为轨道ATK
And now it's part of Northrop Grumman.
而现在它是诺斯罗普·格鲁曼公司的一部分
So it maybe there's a future for the Pegasus, since they've demonstrated this rapid launch capability.
因此 也许飞马座仍然存在未来 因为他们已经验证了这种快速发射能力
Having said that there is only one other Pegasus sitting in storage right now,
话虽如此 现在只有另一枚飞马座放在仓库里
Now equally, there was another launch, which is actually somewhat related.
那么同样 还有另一次发射 这实际上有些相关
Again, in Northrop Grumman Launch to the Department of Defense.
同样是诺斯罗普·格鲁曼公司给国防部提供的发射服务
And this has a really cool badge showing like a,
而这有一个非常酷的徽章 显示像一个
it reminds me of Porco Rosso, so it's like a warthog with a flying mustache and stuff.
它让我想起了红猪 差不多是一个有飞行胡子的疣猪之类的东西
Department of Defense, NRO, badges always the best, let me tell you almost perfect,
国防部的NRO的徽章总是最好的 让我告诉你 这几乎完美
but yeah this was launched in a Minotaur I, and the Minotaur I,
但这是在米诺陶一号中发射的 而米诺陶一号
if you don't know, uses the first two stages of a Minuteman missile.
如果你不知道 其使用的是民兵导弹的前两级
Now I think this is a Minuteman I
那么我想这是一枚民兵一号
and those were deployed from 1962 to 1965, right?
而这些导弹是在1962年至1965年部署的 对吧
Very long time ago.
很久以前了
And then they were decommissioned but the boosters are still around,
然后它们就退役了 但助推器还在
Some of them have been kept in storage, so they can be used as launch vehicles.
其中一些被保存在仓库里 所以它们可以作为运载火箭来使用
And so this booster that launched this payload a few days ago
因此 几天前发射这个有效载荷的助推器
may well be the oldest rocket to ever fly,
很可能是有史以来最古老的火箭
as in time between it actually being built and flying
因为从它实际建造和飞行的时间来看
obviously, the R-7 derived stuff that the USSR and Soviet Union use and sorry
很明显 R-7衍生的运载火箭 在苏联和苏维埃联盟使用的 啊 抱歉
and Russia, pardon me, use it.
是俄罗斯
Has its roots going back to the 1950s.
其也可以追溯到20世纪50年代
But this is actually a piece of hardware dated probably from the sixties.
但这实际上可能是一件60年代制造的设备(而联盟火箭就不是了)
It just blows my mind.
它只是让我感到震惊
There is like Minotaur-C, incidentally, which is a commercial version.
顺便说一下 还有米诺陶-C 那是一个商业版本
That uses a first stage which is based on an ICBM,
它使用一个基于洲际弹道导弹的一级
个人理解这不是使用退役的洲际弹道导弹修改而来，而是重新制造了新的设备
but not actually derived from an ICBM.
但实际上不是从洲际弹道导弹中衍生出来的
The second or third,
而二级和三级
oh, by the way, the Pegasus link is the third and fourth stages of the Minotaur
哦 顺便说一下 与飞马座有联系的是米诺陶的三级和四级
are the top two stages of the Pegasus.
是飞马座的后两级(上面两级)
Now the reason why this isn't seen more often is
现在之所以没有更多地看到这枚火箭的发射 是因为
I think maybe the late 90s, this was developed.
我想也许在其刚开发出来的90年代末
And Orbital Sciences wanted to expand the capabilities, and they basically.
而轨道科学公司想扩大火箭的运载能力 他们基本上
Congress said you can use these Minuteman missiles for launching payloads into orbit,
国会说你可以用这些民兵导弹来发射有效载荷进入轨道
but you're only allowed to do it for government payloads.
但只允许发射政府的有效载荷
And Congress wouldn't allow them to expand that for commercial operations.
国会不允许他们将其扩大到商业载荷上
So when they created the Minotaur-C or, as it was once known, Taurus,
因此 当他们创造了米诺陶-C或者 正如它曾经被称为金牛座的时候
they had to build their own first stages.
他们不得不单独建造一级
And so that kinda robbed it of its capabilities of its cheapness. Let's say.
因此 可以这么说 这相对减少了它的能力和廉价性
Anyway, I'm sure we'll see Minotaur continuing to fly,
无论如何 我相信我们会看到米诺陶继续飞行
because there's a lot of those Minuteman stages and storages, right?
因为还有很多民兵导弹的库存 对吧
Anyway the other sort of really big stuff that's going on right now
总之 现在正在进行的另一种真正的大事是
is like the Global Space Exploration Conference.
全球航天探索大会
It's basically a giant space exploration conferences,
这基本上是一个巨大的航天探索会议
going on right now in St. Petersburg, Russia
现正在俄罗斯的圣彼得堡举行
And while it's had leaders from all of the major space agencies there,
虽然大多数主要的航天机构的领导人都到了那里
either giving talks via Zoom or video conferencing or actually physically there,
要么通过Zoom或者说视频会议进行了会谈 要么实际到场
the thing that I've seen most interesting out of this has been China and Russia.
我看到最有趣的事情是中国和俄罗斯
Russia has basically had Dmitry Rogozin and day one, saying,
基本上 俄罗斯方面来了德米特里·罗戈津 而他第一天说
We are going to work very hard with other partners, specifically China.
我们将与其他伙伴 特别是中国 进行非常深入的合作
We want to launch our Soyuz to the Chinese space station Tiangong.
我们想把我们的联盟号发射到中国的天宫空间站
But that's going to be an interesting one,
但这将是一个有趣的事情
because they're going to have to get buying from the European Arianespace,
因为俄罗斯人将不得不从欧洲的阿丽亚娜航天那里购买(租用)
who have the only Soyuz launch facility,
(因为)阿丽亚娜拥有唯一的联盟火箭发射设施
which is at low enough latitude to actually reach the Chinese Space Station.
其纬度足够低 可以真正到达中国空间站
Chinese Space Station is about 42 degrees north.
中国空间站的倾角在42度左右
Baikonur is 45 degrees, but has problems with dropping debris in Mongolia.
而拜科努尔是45度 但这样发射有在蒙古掉落残骸的问题
and shoot, what's it called?
而 倒霉 它叫什么？
Ah Vostochny is about 52 degrees north or 51 in something,
啊 东方 大约在北纬52度或51度的地方
so basically, if Russia wants to work with China and launch stuff to their space station,
因此 基本上 如果俄罗斯想与中国合作 向他们的空间站发射东西
they are going to have to get the European Space Agency or Arianespace to get on their site,
他们将不得不使用欧洲空间局或阿丽亚娜空间公司的发射场
and they might well do that,
而他们很可能会这样做
because Europe also wants to be involved in another space station project.
因为欧洲也想参与中国空间站的项目
Another side of this is Soyuz when it was being worked on for the ISS,
另外则是 联盟飞船在与国际空间站对接时
They kept on using the old style Soyuz docking adapter,
一直在使用老式的联盟飞船对接适配器
because the new APAS, Androgenous Peripheral Attachment System that Russia invented.
因为新的APAS 即俄罗斯发明的异体同构周边系统
Let's remind us.
(说全称)只是让大家回忆一下
It was too heavy to operate on the Soyuz and have enough margin for operation.
它太重了 无法在联盟飞船上操作 而且操作冗余度也不够多
But that was twenty years ago.
但那是二十年前的事了
Since then, there's been a lot of upgrades to the Soyuz,
从那时起 联盟飞船(以及火箭)已经有了很多的升级
so they might be able to fly these with the docking system,
所以他们可能可以将APAS放在联盟飞船上了
which is suitable for China and fly them from Kuru in South America.
同时这种APAS能兼容中国的标准 并从南美洲的库鲁进行发射
And be able to be part of this project.
并能成为这个项目的一部分
Look, that's small thing.
注意 这是件小事
The big thing is that they're actually talking big time
大事是 他们实际上正在大谈特谈
about a China-Russian International Lunar Research Base.
关于中国-俄罗斯国际月球科研站(ILRS)
And this is a base on the surface of the moon.
而这是一个在月球表面的基地
The timeline they're talking about is for the next five years or so,
他们谈论的时间表是未来五年左右的时间
continue doing reconnaissance is in collaboration between both countries.
在两国之间的合作是继续(对月球)进行侦察
And then move to start actually building out structures on the surface
然后开始在月球表面实际建造结构
that can eventually support landings in 2035.
最终能够支持在2035年着陆
So the diagrams they've got nice slides and stuff,
因此 他们的图表有漂亮的幻灯片和其他的东西
and they show Long March rockets flying alongside,
还显示了长征火箭在一旁飞行
Soyuz to launch payloads initially,
最初 会使用联盟火箭来发射有效载荷
应该是长征九号
and then it's like Angara and Long March 8 or 9 or whatever, launching,
然后就会使用安加拉 还有长征八号或九号之类的发射
or long March 9, I don't know, big heavy lift vehicles.
或者长征九号 我不知道 一种大型重型运载火箭
And Long March 5, actually as well.
还有长征五号 实际上也是如此
Launching stuff to the surface of the moon and eventually putting people on the moon.
把东西发射到月球表面 最终把人送上月球
Now, let's be clear, these timelines are highly aspirational, right?
那么 我们要清楚 这些时间表是非常理想化的 对吧
There's a lot of money involved here.
这里涉及大量的资金
Certainly they are looking for other partners to collaborate with them.
当然 他们正在寻找其他合作伙伴
There would be very happy to have JAXA or European Space Agency also collaborate.
他们将非常高兴让日本宇宙航空研究开发机构或欧洲空间局也进行合作
But building something like that in this amount of time may not be possible,
但是在这么长的时间里建造这样的东西是很难的
especially since it's not even clear that
特别是由于现在还不清楚
扎心了
the Chinese heavy lift rockets will be ready for the construction phase.
中国的重型火箭将准备好进入建造阶段
But, having said that the fact that they're committed, they put this out there is a really, really cool thing,
尽管如此 事实上 他们对此的承诺与发布 是一件非常酷的事情
and I'd like to see it eventually succeed, whatever the time scale.
而我希望看到它最终成功 无论时间尺度如何
Very likely that the US, with Artemis will return to the moon first.
非常有可能的是 美国的阿尔忒弥斯将首先返回月球
But the question is, will always how long are they going to stay.
但总在问的一个问题是 他们会停留多久
How much of a commitment is this to like long term exploitation and exploration of the moon?
这对长期开发和探索月球之类的事业 投入有多大？
There was a few different launch sites that were shown over the surface of the moon.
(回到ILRS) 在月球表面上有几个不同的发射场被显示出来
Most of them were at low latitude,
他们中的大多数都在低纬度地区
but one was an Amundsen Crater at the south pole, I believe.
但有一个我觉得是位于南极的阿蒙森环形山
Yeah, so anyway, that's what's going on,
是的 所以无论如何 这就是要发生的事情
oh, and also, of course, with a launch well, practically hours away.
哦 还有 当然 距离发射还有好几个小时
China have finally announced the crew for their first flight to their space station.
(在这之前) 中国终于宣布了他们首次飞往空间站的人员名单
And because I'm doing this for memory, I don't actually remember their names,
因为我是根据记忆来做的视频 实际上不记得他们的名字
so I'm going to like add it in a thing over the top to show you,
所以我打算把它加在上面给你们看
but three Chinese astronauts, I know they're all male,
但是这三位中国宇航员 我知道他们都是男性
and two of them have previously flown into space on Shenzhou.
而他们中的两个以前曾乘坐神舟飞船进入过太空
Well, third, it's going to be his first flight,
嗯 至于第三名航天员 将是他的第一次飞行
and they're going to spend several months on the space station, their space station,
而他们将在空间站上度过几个月 具体来说是他们的空间站
根据www.xinhuanet.com/2021-06/16/c_1127566274.htm，是两次eva
including an EVA to demonstrate the capabilities,
包括一个EVA来验证能力
and hopefully move their construction forward,
并希望能推动他们的建设
because this is a modular space station, unlike Tiangong 1 and 2,
因为这是一个模块化的空间站 与天宫一号和二号不同
this is going to be required actual unpacking of materials, deployment of stuff etc.
这将需要实际拆开材料 部署设备等
Also today, there was a spacewalk on ISS
同样在今天 国际空间站上有一次太空行走
根据 https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roll_Out_Solar_Array ，应该是ISS ROSA
to start installing the new iROSA, the Improved(ISS) Roll Out Solar Arrays.
开始安装新的iROSA 即国际空间站柔性太阳能电池阵列
They didn't complete all their tasks.
他们并没有完成所有的任务
They had a few problems.
他们遇到了一些问题
In fact, they did have a problem with one of the spacesuits.
事实上 确实有一个宇航服出了问题
And you know, those spacesuits are on the space station are starting to show their age.
而且你知道 空间站上的那些宇航服已经开始显旧了
I mean they were built decades ago under being refurbished.
我的意思是 它们是几十年前建造的 正在进行翻新
So it's not uncommon to find problems with them.
所以发现它们的问题并不罕见
Hopefully, by the time that US is landing people on the moon,
希望到了美国载人登月的时候
they will have newer space suits to to do that in.
会有更新的宇航服来做这件事
Because yeah the ones are used in space are kind of heavy.
因为是的 目前在太空中使用的宇航服是有点重的
They're kind of bulky.
他们有点笨重
They're not really the kind of things you want to walk in.
并不是你想(去登月要)穿的那种东西
The legs don't actually move well enough for that.
腿实际上不能很好地移动
So anyway, yeah, from the end of the world,
那么无论如何 是的 从世界的尽头
this is Scott Manley saying, fly safe.
这里是Scott Manley在说 切记 注意飞行安全
从这里开始是原视频剪辑失误，没有有效信息……